מזל טוב, Mazel tov, today's דף daf is קטז, Kuf Tes Zayin,
116. We pick up at the bottom of קטו עמוד ב, Kuf
Tes Vav Amud Beis, we're in the middle of the whole discussion
of like the pre-history, I guess, of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and about bringing קרבנות korbanos and we're now talking about what happened
in terms of initially the עבודה avoda was with the wasn't כהנים,
kohanim, it was the firstborn. We actually saw that there was a
debate whether it was already the כהנים kohanim from the time of
הר סיני, Har Sinai, נדב ואביהוא, Nadav v'Avihu, or was it the
firstborn all the way until the משכן Mishkan
and then we're talking also about, right, about what was the sort
of accepted in terms of sacrifices in that prior period.
According to the ברייתא baraisa that we read basically, it said that
the עבודה avoda initially even at הר סיני, Har Sinai, it was
with the firstborn
and any animals as long as they were כשר kosher even if
they had blemishes, male, female, etc., etc. Okay,
an interesting parenthesis is that even though all of this stuff did
not really start until the משכן Mishkan was erected and the beginning
of ויקרא, Vayikra, so all the rules were different. The one rule
that it says actually was in place was the details of how
you bring an עולה. olah. So that was a little bit bizarre
because here we're sort of saying the details already started at הר
סיני, Har Sinai, but here we're saying for all these major things
the details did not yet start. Anyway, that was contrasted with an
approach that said that no, no, no, the עבודה avoda is with
the כהנים, kohanim, it did not really get to this question about
which types of קרבנות, korbanos, but at least the כהנים kohanim started
here, but the specifics about how the עולה olah was brought, that
waited until הר סיני. Har Sinai. So that was interesting about the
question of the specifics of the עולה. olah. But now we're going
to focus on this part
about what types of קרבנות korbanos were in effect, you know, leading
up to the משכן Mishkan and this is not just from הר
סיני Har Sinai leading up to the משכן, Mishkan, this is from
all the pre-history leading up to the משכן, Mishkan, what could be
sort of brought as a קרבן? korban? Okay, so we pick up
with the bottom of קטו עמוד ב Kuf Tes Vav Amud Beis
and the גמרא Gemara says like this, three lines from the bottom.
אמר מר כל שהם להקריב, Amar mar, hachol shehem lehakriv,
you could bring all types of animals in this pre-משכן Mishkan period.
מנא הני מילי, Minani milei, where is this from? So אמר רב
הונא דאמר קרא, Amar Rav Huna d'amar kra, the verse says, so
we're going to go back to the very first bringing of קרבנות,
korbanos, well not the first, the first is קין והבל, Kayin v'Hevel,
but anyway, but we're going to go back all the way to
נח Noach and we're going to assume that whatever was true with
נח Noach sort of remains in effect until the until the משכן.
Mishkan. Now again, this is interesting because as we're going to see,
you know, there's a classic question of when did we stop being
בני נח Bnei Noach and start being בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, when
did different rules start applying? So, you know, you could say that
all of this is until like הר סיני. Har Sinai. Again, that
gets to the question, maybe we should assume that the details were
already there at הר סיני. Har Sinai. But anyway, so these פסוקים
psukim are certainly good evidence in terms of what it was until
הר סיני. Har Sinai. We're going to assume it's going to remain
that way all the way up until the משכן Mishkan when ויקרא
Vayikra was given and all the specifics were given. Anyway, so let's
take a look. מנא הני מילי, Minani milei, אמר רב הונא דאמר
קרא, Amar Rav Huna d'amar kra, the verse says, ויבן נח מזבח
להשם, Vayiven Noach mizbe'ach l'Hashem, he he built an altar, ויקח מכל
הבהמה הטהורה, Vayikach mikol habeheima hatorah, from all kosher animals, so it
did not have to only be like the ox and the and
the and the goats and the sheep. ומכל העוף הטהור, Umikol ha'of
hatorah, all kosher birds, and it didn't also say that there was
any problem about male or female or any difference if they had
a blemish. The basic point being that until the law changed, which
it did presumably when the משכן Mishkan was erected and ויקרא Vayikra
gave all the details, all all kosher animals were accepted with no
distinctions, male, female, blemish, not blemish, and so on. בהמה כמשמעון, Beheima
kemashma'on, now בהמה beheima sounds like all בהמות. beheimos. חיה בכלל בהמה,
Chaya bichlal beheima, we're going to assume חיות chayas are included, so
at that pre pre-history
period or whatever, if you wanted to bring a deer or something
of that of that of that nature, be my guest, right? זכר
ונקבה תמימים ובעלי מומין, Zachar u'nekeiva, temimim u'baalei mumin, and there's no
distinction here, male, female, blemish, not blemish, it's all okay. Okay, so
we'll skip the parenthesis. לאפוקי מחוסר איבר דלא, Le'apukei mechusar eiver delo,
the one thing however that we're going to assume is not included
is something missing a limb. How do we know that wouldn't be
okay and that's also what the גמרא's Gemara attitude is to בני
נח? Bnei Noach? That בני נח Bnei Noach can bring a קרבן
korban but a missing a limb is פסול. posul. Actually, it's also
what the גמרא's Gemara attitude is to birds, that if a bird
is missing a limb, even though there's no idea of unblemished by
a bird because it never says תמים tamim by a bird, missing
a limb is a problem. So how do you know even in
this pre-משכן Mishkan period a missing a limb was an issue?
דאמר רבי אליעזר, D'amar Rabbi Eliezer, מנין למחוסר איבר שנאסרו לבני נח?
Minayin le'mechusar eiver she'nasru li'vnei Noach? How do you know missing a
limb is a problem for בני נח, Bnei Noach, which is what
was in effect until the law changed even for us as the,
you know, the בני ישראל? Bnei Yisrael? תלמוד
לומר ומכל החי מכל בשר, Talmud lomar, umikol hachai mikol basar, from
this is the animals he takes onto the תיבה, teva, from all
alive, from all flesh. אמר תורה הבא בהמה שחיין ראשי איברים שלו.
Amar Torah, havei beheima shechayin rashei evarim shelo. Why do you have
to say ומכל החי, umikol hachai, all alive? So it means that
all of its limbs are still intact. Somehow I do not know
even how you're going to do a דרשה drasha from ומכל החי,
umikol hachai, I'm not exactly sure how that leads to the idea.
All of it has to be alive.
Yeah, so I do not know. I mean, I guess, okay. Missing
something. Missing something. Okay, fine. All of it has to be alive.
All the limbs have to be intact. Now the גמרא Gemara says
ודילמא למעוטי טרפה. Vedilma l'mueitei Treifa. Wait, maybe מכל החי Micol Hachay
means it has to be fully alive, which means that it can't
be a טרפה Treifa because the presumption is that a טרפה Treifa
is an animal that's going to die in a relatively short amount
of time. So maybe that's what it's doing, excluding a טרפה. Treifa.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, ההוא לחיות זרע נפקא. Hahu milechayot
zera nafka. No, because that we get from it also says that
the animals have to be to bring forth seed, and the assumption
is that a טרפה Treifa cannot give birth or cannot sire a
child. So actually, so that's. By the way, it's interesting. So although
it doesn't matter that it's blemished or unblemished, it does matter that
it's not missing a limb and it does matter that it's not
a טרפה. Treifa. So that we've actually now added, it can't be
a טרפה. Treifa. One wonders about other types of פסולים. Psulim. What
about an animal used in bestiality? If that was the whole sin
of the מבול Mabul or whatever, would that be okay? So the
גמרא Gemara isn't fully exploring that, but טרפה Treifa and lacking a
limb would be no good. טרפה Treifa we know to exclude from
the verse of of לחיות זרע. Lechayot Zera. So the גמרא Gemara
says, הניחא למאן דאמר טרפה אינה יולדת. Hani nicha leman de'amar Treifa
eina yoledet. That's good if you assume that a טרפה Treifa can't
give birth and presumably also can't sire a child, I guess. אלא
למאן דאמר טרפה יולדת מאי למימרא? Ella leman de'amar Treifa yoledet mai
l'meimra? But if a טרפה Treifa can give birth, מכל החי Micol
Hachay so there לחיות זרע Lechayot Zera doesn't implicitly exclude a טרפה.
Treifa. So we should be focus so מכל החי Micol Hachay should
be focused on טרפה Treifa and we won't know this idea of
missing a limb. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, אמר קרא אתך
בדומים לך. Amar kra itcha bedomim lach. No, no, no. We already
know to exclude טרפה Treifa because the verse it says take on
the on the ark with you. So with you means that it
has to be similar to you. And the same way you know
you aren't a טרפה, Treifa, we know that the בהמות Beheimot can't
be a טרפה. Treifa. So we're left with מכל החי Micol Hachay
to be about limbs. So the גמרא Gemara says, how do you
know Noah wasn't a טרפה? Treifa? So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא
נח גופיה טרפה הוי? Vedilma Noach gufei Treifa havay? Wait, maybe Noah
was a טרפה? Treifa? Maybe even though the animals are like with
you, like you, how do you know that excludes טרפה? Treifa? So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, תמים כתיב ביה. Tamim ksiv bey. It
says that he was perfect.
Perfect means obviously presumably no inner injuries. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ודילמא תמים בדרכיו? Vedilma tamim bedrachav? Maybe it just means, like which
obviously is what it does mean, that he was like perfect and
righteous in his actions. It doesn't mean that physically he was a
hundred percent healthy. So צדיק כתיב ביה. Tzaddik ksiv bey. It says
צדיק, Tzaddik, that already means righteous in his actions. So תמים Tamim
actually means that he was physically healthy. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no. ודילמא תמים בדרכיו צדיק במעשיו. Vedilma tamim bedrachav tzaddik b'maasav. I
like this, it's a very nice distilled distinction of these two aspects.
Maybe תמים Tamim means perfect in his character traits. If you look
at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says תמים בדרכיו ענו
וסבלן. Tamim bedrachav anav v'savlan. Like humble, patient. Like he and צדיק
Tzaddik means צדיק במעשיו, Tzaddik b'maasav, how his actions were righteous. And
you can have that, you can have people that maybe their character
is not so great but they work on how they act and
their actions are correct. You can have people, I don't know, maybe
they're wonderful in terms of their character traits but they're not whatever,
they stay at home all day, they don't do any whatever. So
it's interesting to distinguish between this question of a character, an ethical
character, or one's character, which is like what מוסר Mussar often focuses
on, and the צדיק במעשיו, Tzaddik b'maasav, which is often what like
the הלכה Halacha focuses on, how are you acting?
Anyway, so when it says he's a תמים Tamim and he's a
צדיק, Tzaddik, those could be two aspects of his character and his
action, but it doesn't actually refer to his physical health. So we
still don't know that Noah wasn't a טרפה. Treifa. So we still
don't know how to exclude a טרפה. Treifa. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, no. ודיל so the גמרא Gemara says, no. אי סלקא
דעתך דנח גופיה טרפה הוי Iy salka daitach d'Noach gufei Treifa havay
if Noah was a טרפה, Treifa, מי אמר ליה לנח דכוותך עייל
שלמים לא תעייל? Mi amar lei l'Noach d'chvaseich ayeil sheleimim lo tayeil?
It wouldn't make sense that God would say, I want you to
take animals just like you, I want to make sure you take
טרפות Treifas on the ark. No, obviously if God is saying take
like you, then that must mean, maybe he wants animals that are
have good character traits or that are צדיקים. Tzaddikim. But anyway, so
clearly the אתך Itcha is implicitly sort of it's only meaningful if
we assume that Noah was healthy and the point is take healthy
animals like you. So once that's true from אתך, Itcha, so therefore
מכל החי Micol Hachay is coming to exclude animals that are missing
a limb. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומאחר דנפקא
ליה מאתך לחיות זרע למה לי? Ume'achar denafke lei me'itcha lechayot zera
lama li? So what's לחיות זרע Lechayot Zera doing? אתך Itcha tells
you not a טרפה. Treifa. מכל החי Micol Hachay tells you not
missing a limb. Why does the verse say לחיות זרע, Lechayot Zera,
which is obviously what do you mean why it's saying לחיות זרע?
Lechayot Zera? That's why you're taking the animals on in order that
you can repopulate the world. Which is basically what the גמרא Gemara
says.
So מהו דתימא אתך לצוותא בעלמא, Mahu d'teima itcha l'tzatzava b'alma, no,
maybe just take on the animals so you don't get bored on
the ark, it was before TV. So that they'd be your company.
אפילו זקן אפילו סריס קא משמע לן Afilu zaken afilu saris kamashma
lan no, the reason you're taking on the animals is not so
you don't get bored, it's so that they can repopulate the world.
Fine. Anyway, that's how you get the idea that from Noah we
see all animals, but they have to be טהור, Tahor, they have
to be kosher animals, but it doesn't matter yes blemish, no blemish.
The one thing that we're adding though is can't be missing a
limb or can't be a טרפה. Treifa. טהורים אבל לא טמאים, Tehorim
aval lo tmeim, have to be kosher animals. So now the גמרא
Gemara has a question. I get how you get it because it
says מכל הבהמה הטהורה, Micol habeheima hatehora, but the question is isn't
that a little anachronistic? The idea of what's kosher and what's not
kosher wasn't until the time of that we got the תורה. Torah.
None of that is hinted to, I mean, it's hinted to here,
but there's no indication that prior to that there was a concept
of kosher and not kosher animals. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי
הוי טמא וטהור בההיא שעתא, umi havei tamei vetahor behahee sha'ata, since
when did the idea of kosher and not kosher apply at that
time? Okay. אמר רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן. amar Rebbi
Yishmael bar Nachmani amar Rebbi Yonatan. Now here there's an important different
גירסא. girsa. Our גירסא girsa is מאותן שלא נעבדה בהן עבירה, me'otan
shelo navda bahen aveira, those that were
not involved in the acts of bestiality. The problem with this, it
has nothing to do with טמא וטהור tamei vetahor from our focus.
Our focus is that you could do kosher animals for קרבנות, korbanot,
not non-kosher species of animals.
And also the problem is going to be because, Michael, what does
תורה Torah say by נח? Noach? Did the טמא tamei animals go
on the תיבה? teiva? Of course. Of course they did. If they
didn't go on the תיבה, teiva, what are we doing with lions
and whatever and bears nowadays? What's the difference what the תורה Torah
says about the טהור tahor and the טמא tamei animals?
Well, depends. Sometimes you have שבעה שבעה. shiva shiva.
Right. So it says that there were seven of each of the
טהור, tahor, although sometimes it sounds like there was two of everything.
Okay. But and then it says that נח Noach brought up הבהמה
הטהורה habehema hatehora when he brought it as a קרבן, korban, which
is how we know you can only use kosher animals. But if
the תורה Torah is saying that טהור tahor and טמא, tamei, the
difference is whether נעבדה בהן עבירה, navda bahen aveira, then that means
that they actually had on the
תיבה teiva animals that were involved in bestiality. That doesn't seem to
make sense. So this actually what it's doing is it's borrowing from
another discussion, and which is what leads to this גירסא girsa question.
Because in another place the גמרא Gemara asks another question, which is
it says what animals came on the תיבה? teiva? The תורה Torah
says איש ואשתו, ish ve'ishto, husband and wife. So the גמרא Gemara
says I don't understand, since when did the animals adopt the institution
of marriage? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
איש ואשתו ish ve'ishto means animals שלא נעבדה בהן עבירה, shelo navda
bahen aveira, שנדבקו במינם, shenidpaku baminam, that they were not used in
bestiality, they weren't whatever, inter-species breeding. And therefore what the גמרא Gemara
says elsewhere is that whether טהור tahor or
טמא, tamei, whatever whether kosher or not kosher, no animals that were
involved in inter-species breeding or whatever went on the תיבה, teiva, which
makes sense. Okay, but that's not our point. Our point, that means
whether טהור tahor or טמא, tamei, they were all איש ואשתו, ish
ve'ishto, they were all kept to their own species. Okay. We're though
focusing on the טהור טמא tahor tamei distinction, both of which were
on the תיבה. teiva. So the better גירסא girsa here is not
שלא נעבדה בהן עבירה, shelo navda bahen aveira, but if you look
at the side, מאותן העתידין להיטהר. me'otan ha'atidin lehitaher. You're right. It
doesn't mean that at this stage by נח Noach there's a concept
of I mean, there is a concept, but it doesn't mean that
the laws of כשרות kashrut apply yet. When it says that טהור
tahor animals were seven and the טמא tamei were two and the
טהור tahor were the ones brought for קרבנות, korbanot, it means that
the ones that eventually the תורה Torah was going to declare. Well,
yes. So elsewhere רש"י על התורה Rashi al haTorah says that מלמד
שלמד נח תורה, melamed shelamad Noach Torah, already knew
תורה. Torah. מלמד ששנה נח תורה melamed sheshana Noach Torah or something
like that.
So yes. Now of course what you could also say is, although
the גמרא Gemara never exactly says this, but like רמב"ן Ramban points
out by the whole idea of יבום, yibbum, the whole idea with
יהודה ותמר Yehuda veTamar and his whatever, בוא אל אשת אחיך, bo
el eshet achicha, that some of these concepts existed before the תורה
Torah actually commanded them and maybe in slightly different form. So the
idea that there was a concept of certain types of ways of
categorizing animals and God hadn't commanded don't eat, but that there was
a way of thinking of them as different classes of animals, you
could say that. גמרא Gemara isn't exactly saying that. It's saying העתידין
להיטהר, ha'atidin lehitaher, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that נח Noach
learned תורה. Torah. רש"י Rashi says that elsewhere על התורה, al haTorah,
רש"י Rashi says we hear we see from here that נח Noach
learned תורה. Torah. Okay.
So how did this גירסא girsa שלא נעבדה בהן עבירה shelo navda
bahen aveira get in here?
Because the statement of רבי יונתן Rebbi Yonatan was this statement of
רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן Rebbi Yishmael bar Nachmani amar
Rebbi Yonatan was שלא נעבדה בהן עבירה shelo navda bahen aveira was
said in reference to איש ואשתו, ish ve'ishto, and we're just sort
of saying something similar here, so that sort of led to the
confusion. Okay.
מאותן העתידין להיטהר. me'otan ha'atidin lehitaher. So yeah, you're right. It wasn't
yet commanded, but at least eventually this is how they were going
to be categorized and that's the ones that came in seven, those
that would eventually be kosher. Okay. Now מנא ידע, mena yada, now
how did they know? So as opposed to saying as again what
רש"י Rashi and the מהרש"א Maharsha has long discussion why רש"י Rashi
doesn't say what the גמרא Gemara is about to say. רש"י על
התורה Rashi al haTorah says that נח Noach knew because נח Noach
learned תורה Torah already. But the גמרא gemara doesn't give that answer.
How did נח Noach know if they hadn't yet been commanded what's
kosher and טרפה? treifa? How did he know which were the טהור
tahor ones and which were the
טמא tamei ones? So כי דרב חסדא, ki d'Rav Chisda, like רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says. דאמר רב חסדא, d'amar Rav Chisda, העבירן לפני
התיבה, he'eviran lifnei hateiva, he passed them before the
ark. כל שהתיבה קולטתו בידוע שהוא טהור, kol shehateiva kolat'to beyadua shehu
tahor, if the תיבה teiva would absorb them, like you know if
they would be able to get in the door, you would know
they were טהור. tahor. אין התיבה קולטתו, ein hateiva kolat'to, if it
doesn't absorb them, בידוע שהוא טמא, beyadua shehu tamei, you would know
they were טמא. tamei. Now that doesn't work because the טמא tamei
did come in, they just came in two as opposed to seven.
So again this is a text that originally applied to the idea
of איש ואשתו ish ve'ishto and that whether טהור tahor or טמא,
tamei, only the ones that were not involved in sin came in,
and then you could say that the תיבה teiva just wouldn't accept
and they got totally rejected if they had been involved in an
act of sinful sexual intercourse. Here we're using it by analogy. It's
not the exact statement. And here we're But so the way you
would have to say it although the גמרא gemara doesn't say it,
is that the טהור tohor ones you were able to get seven
of them in the ark, the טמא tamei ones when you tried
to get in more than two, you couldn't get them in. But
what we're doing is we're taking a similar discussion of the idea
of whether טהור tohor or טמא tamei was only those that weren't
used in an עבירה aveira and we're applying it here. Okay, and
we're saying here too, it was that we're going to be טהור,
tohor, we're going to be טמא tamei and the תיבה teva would
determine, you know, would let you know which ones which ones were
which. Okay, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu אמר אמר קרא amar amar kra
the פסוק pasuk says והבאים זכר ונקבה ve'haba'im zachar u'nekeivah הבאים מאליהם.
haba'im me'aleihem. No, the animals came on their own. So the animals
that came two at a time were the טמא tamei ones. The
animals that came in groups of seven, those were the טהור tohor
ones. Okay, אמר מר amar mar והכל הקריבו עולות. vehakol hikrivu olos.
So they could bring all types of animals as long as they're
kosher, but you could only bring an עולה olah pre-the משכן. mishkan.
So the גמרא gemara says, so the גמרא gemara says עולות אין
שלמים לא? olos in shelamim lo? Are you telling me that they
could not bring שלמים shelamim before? I mean I guess the idea
of a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham was completely foreign because
the whole idea of sin and so on was not a relevant
concept at that time. So the I mean whatever it was, I
mean obviously קין והבל Kayin ve'Hevel but whatever, that whole system wasn't
relevant. But therefore but the so once you're excluding חטאת chatas and
אשם, asham, the relevant the only other really relevant thing to talk
about is a שלמים. shelamim. So you're emphasizing, right? It was all
עולות olos and not שלמים. shelamim. So the גמרא gemara says is
that really true?
והכתיב ויזבחו זבחים שלמים לה׳ פרים. ve'hachtiv vayizbechu zevachim shelamim la'Hashem parim.
Right there at הר סיני. Har Sinai. And we're saying that all
the way up until until the משכן, mishkan, until ויקרא, Vayikra, it
was only it was you know this thing. All animals but only
עולות. olos. But what do you mean? It sounds like at the
foot of הר סיני Har Sinai it's explicit that they brought שלמים.
shelamim. So the גמרא gemara says אלא אימא הכל הקריבו עולות. ela
eima hakol hikrivu olos. All people brought עולות. olos. Meaning that that
even let me just to just to cross my I's with the
yeah הכל hakol says בין ישראל בין בני נח הקריבו עולות. bein
Yisrael bein bnei Noach hikrivu olos. Okay. So so only בני נח
bnei Noach only brought everybody brought עולות olos whether ישראל Yisrael or
whether בני נח. bnei Noach. Okay. So yeah, let's take a look.
הכל הקריבו עולות ושלמים. hakol hikrivu olos u'shelamim. והתניא אבל שלמים לא
כי אם עולות. vehatanya aval shelamim lo ki im olos. עולות אין
שלמים לא? olos in shelamim lo? So anyway only עולות. olos. So
it says says כמאן דאמר לא קרבו שלמים בני נח. keman d'amar
lo karvu shelamim bnei Noach. Yeah, בני נח bnei Noach did not
bring שלמים. shelamim. But the problem here is not the problem but
what we're doing is until now we basically have been saying this
idea, all animals or whatever, all until the משכן, mishkan, right? This
is base and we learned it out from נח. Noach. This is
basically been saying, okay here I'll draw my ark with all of
the animals on it. Okay. I won't draw all anyway here are
my animals on the ark over. Here's from the time of נח,
Noach, right? Till we basically been saying that's how we know from
it says that he brought all animals or whatever, all of that
until this time. Okay. And that's how we know that all animals
whether it has a blemish as long as they're kosher etc., we
all learn it off from נח Noach until we got the new
laws at the משכן. mishkan. Now when we're making this difference between
עולות olos and שלמים shelamim because here it says that they brought
שלמים shelamim at הר סיני, Har Sinai, what we're actually saying is
is that no at הר סיני Har Sinai here I'll make my
little הר סיני Har Sinai here. Okay. Anyway so here you see
this is like doing bible stories for kids. Anyway what we're saying
is although all of this is true and the assumption sort of
is we're all under the rules of בני נח bnei Noach until
the משכן. mishkan. Now what we're saying is no at הר סיני
Har Sinai it goes from בני נח bnei Noach to בני ישראל.
bnei Yisrael. Right? Which is always an important question like when did
we get that status of בני ישראל? bnei Yisrael? When we left
מצרים, Mitzrayim, at מעמד הר סיני ma'amad Har Sinai and so on.
So assuming it's מעמד הר סיני ma'amad Har Sinai which is the
most obvious time we got that status. The גמרא's Gemara whole discussions
about conversion and גירות geirus and learning קבלת מצוות kabbalas mitzvos and
all these things focuses on הר סיני. Har Sinai. Okay. And that's
when you start getting the מצוות. mitzvos. Okay. So anyway so basically
so somehow
these laws of the קרבנות korbanos apply until they're changed, right? So
the idea of all animals and a male or female blemish whatever,
even though here we're בני ישראל bnei Yisrael here, those laws are
still in effect until they're changed at the משכן mishkan at the
beginning of ויקרא. Vayikra. But some laws because there is a status
change that occurs at הר סיני Har Sinai we become בני ישראל,
bnei Yisrael, some laws could change at that moment. Not necessarily but
they could. So what we're saying happened for example the עולה, olah,
the details of the עולה olah was an example we gave before.
So one of the changes we're going to say gets introduced here
is that here we get allowed to bring שלמים. shelamim. Okay. So
therefore or that gets included. So these laws of all kosher animals
or whatever, all apply even though we become בני ישראל bnei Yisrael
here, those those some of those only get changed at the משכן.
mishkan. Okay. Whereas the idea of שלמים shelamim that gets introduced at
the foot of הר סיני Har Sinai so as בני ישראל bnei
Yisrael we're able to bring שלמים. shelamim. All right. So that's the
that's so so meaning hidden in this answer though is like introducing
this question right about like what status did we have and when
did these laws change you know you know. Exactly. So thank you,
so hold on to that thought.
Okay, דאיתמר, de'itmar, it was taught, רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי ברבי חנינא,
Rabbi Elazar berabi Yosei berabi Chanina, חד אמר קרבו שלמי בני נח
chad amar kirevu Shelamim Bnei Noach וחד אמר
לא קרבו,
vechad amar
lo
kirevu, debate whether בני נח Bnei Noach brought שלמים. Shelamim.
So this ברייתא braita that says it was all עולות olot means
that everybody brings, you
know, the עולה olah is the one קרבן korban that is shared
by everyone, okay, that means that בני נח Bnei Noach did not
bring שלמים, Shelamim, that only עולה olah is something that we all
bring. מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר קרבו שלמי בני נח? mai ta'ama deman
de'amar kirevu Shelamim Bnei Noach? What's the basis? Michael's going to the
theological basis, which we'll get to, but what's the textual basis that
בני נח Bnei Noach brought שלמים? Shelamim? Okay, דכתיב, dechtiv, the verse
says, והבל הביא גם הוא מבכרות צאנו ומחלביהן, veHevel hevi gam hu
mibechorot tzonu umichelveihen, which is actually not a bad proof, right? The
firstborn and their fat. So the fat sound like the fats were
on the altar and the meat was eaten, and that is what
is paradigmatic about the שלמים Shelamim as Michael pointed out, is not,
you know, the עולה olah is that it is all עולה, olah,
it is all put up, it is all burnt. The שלמים Shelamim
is that you actually eat from the meat. Okay, so if you're
only putting up the fat, that's a type of a שלמים. Shelamim.
איזהו דבר שחלבו קרב לגבי מזבח ואין כולו קרב לגבי מזבח הוי
אומר זה שלמים. eizehu davar shechelbo karev legabei mizbeiach ve'ein kulo karev
legabei mizbeiach hevei omer zeh Shelamim. So that's a שלמים, Shelamim, that's
what's paradigmatic about a שלמים, Shelamim, that you get to eat the
meat. So that sounds like already from the time of הבל Hevel
we're bringing that type of a קרבן. korban. מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר
לא קרבו? mai ta'ama deman de'amar lo kirevu? What's the basis of
saying they did not bring שלמים? Shelamim? דכתיב, dechtiv, עורי צפון ובואי
תימן. uri tzafon uvo'i teiman. Okay, stir yourself to the north and
come from the south, שיתנער אומה שמעשיה בצפון, shitna'er uma shema'aseiha batzafon,
should be turned over the nation that brings only things from the
north, because an עולה olah is in the north, which is ironic
because if non-Jews are bringing sacrifices, they're not only bringing it to
the north, you know, that's like a הלכה halacha in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash that you bring the עולה olah and קדשי קדשים,
kodshei kodashim, you know, at the north of the altar, but שיתנער
אומה שמעשיה בצפון, shitna'er uma shema'aseiha batzafon, should be overturned the nation
that the nations that only bring עולות, olot, ותבוא אומה שמעשיה בצפון
ובדרום, vutavo uma shema'aseiha batzafon uvadarom, and be replaced by the nation
that brings animals, sacrifices that come from the north and the south,
meaning עולה olah and שלמים. Shelamim. Okay, that's pretty weak proof. Okay,
so anyway, הגמרא haGemara says, ומר נמי הא כתיב ומחלביהן. umar nami
ha ketiv umichelveihen. Now if you say that בני נח Bnei Noach
didn't bring שלמים, Shelamim, what do you do with the verse by
הבל? Hevel? It says from their fat. משמניהן, mishmeneihen, it means from
the from the fat animals, but it doesn't mean only the fats
of the animals. But it still doesn't mean that they ate, you
know, they ate the rest of it. It could be that like
they just, you know, the rest of it got thrown in the,
you know, the garbage. Maybe, a big waste of meat. ומר נמי
הא כתיב עורי צפון, umar nami ha ketiv uri tzafon, which obviously
is the very weak proof of anything, הוא בקיבוץ גלויות הוא דכתיב,
hu bekibutz galuyot hu dechtiv, no, that's just saying that all the
nations are going to come from all over the world, okay, at
the time of the משיח. Mashiach. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, והא כתיב, veha ketiv, fine, so fine, but we have this
assertion, not שלמים. Shelamim. But now the problem is that a lot
of the verses are going to sound like בני נח Bnei Noach
did bring שלמים, Shelamim, okay. But wait, wait, wait, so but are
we saying that this ברייתא braita is not going according to that
opinion that says that they brought שלמים Shelamim or are we just
reinterpreting the הכל כשרין לעולה hakol kesherin le'olah means anybody could bring
an עולה? olah? Yes, that's what we're interpreting it. Anybody could bring
an עולה, olah, עולה olah was the only, and not necessarily שלמים.
Shelamim. And not, right, but שלמים Shelamim was only for בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, והא כתיב ויאמר
משה גם אתה תתן בידינו זבחים ועולות, veha ketiv vayomer Moshe gam
atah titein beyadeinu zevachim ve'olot, now זבחים zevachim because, so I did
a little reading last night from what's his name, commentary on ויקרא,
Vayikra, Jacob Milgrom, the guy who writes that whole huge book on
ויקרא. Vayikra. Anyway, whatever. I'll come up with a name. Anyway, so,
so, anyway, so the point is by שלמים Shelamim it's always, you
know, זבחי שלמים. zivchei Shelamim. The word זבח zevach is always used
in conjunction with the word שלמים, Shelamim, and the basic assumption is
because exactly this, that what's classic about a שלמים Shelamim is that
the meat was eaten, and the word זבח zevach on the one
hand it means slaughtered, right, this is called זבחים, zevachim, right, and
you know, but, but nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara also often assumes the
word זבח zevach means שלמים Shelamim because the classic meaning of זבח
zevach is slaughtering for eating of the meat, and therefore that's why
it's זבחי שלמים zivchei Shelamim because שלמים Shelamim the meat was eaten.
So now we have this verse that says זבח פסח, zevach Pesach,
right, exactly, yeah. So it says, so it says here that you
will give בידינו זבחים ועולות beyadeinu zevachim ve'olot ועשינו לה' אלהינו, ve'asinu
l'Adonai Eloheinu, so you see that they were doing שלמים Shelamim and
that was before הר סיני. Har Sinai. So the גמרא Gemara says
זבחים לאכילה ועולות להקרבה. zevachim la'achilah ve'olot lehakravah. No, that doesn't mean
that they the גם אתה תתן בידינו זבחים, gam atah titein beyadeinu
zevachim, we're going to have a feast with some meat and עולות,
olot, and עולות olot as the sacrifice. Okay. והא כתיב ויקח יתרו
חתן משה עולה וזבחים לאלהים, veha ketiv vayikach Yitro chotein Moshe olah
uzevachim l'Elohim, so there also by יתרו Yitro it says עולה וזבחים
olah uzevachim and that was before הר סיני. Har Sinai. So the
גמרא Gemara says ההוא לאחר מתן תורה הוא דכתיב, hahu le'achar matan
Torah hu dechtiv, that was after מתן תורה. matan Torah. Now first
of all the מהרש"א Maharsha says why didn't the גמרא Gemara say
also... There that the זבחים zvachim was the meat? Why did it?
Because there it says עולה וזבחים לאלהים. olah uzvachim leilokim. So clearly
the זבחים zvachim was to God. Now by saying it was after
מתן תורה matan Torah is an interesting question because the question is
whose קרבן korban was it? Was it יתרו Yitro bringing it? It
says יתרו Yitro brought it. So even if it was after מתן
תורה, matan Torah, right, it's presuming that יתרו Yitro also converted, right?
Which is also an interesting question and a debate. So in order
to explain how יתרו Yitro could have brought a שלמים, shlamim, you
have to say two things: It was after מתן תורה, matan Torah,
so now בני ישראל bnei Yisrael are bringing a שלמים, shlamim, and
יתרו Yitro converted, and now he's בני ישראל bnei Yisrael and he's
bringing שלמים. shlamim. He gave it to Moses and they were מקריב
שלמים. makriv shlamim. Well, I know, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't sound
that way. It says that he was bringing, ויקח יתרו. Vayikach Yisro.
Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says, הני למאן דאמר יתרו אחר
מתן תורה היה. hani leman de'amar Yisro achar matan Torah haya. Now
we get into this fun debate. That's good if we say that
יתרו Yitro came after מתן תורה, matan Torah, so he could have
brought it and brought a שלמים. shlamim. אלא למאן דאמר יתרו קודם
מתן תורה היה מאי איכא למימר? ela leman de'amar Yisro kodem matan
Torah haya mai ika lemeimar? What do you do if it says
that he was before מתן תורה, matan Torah, how did he bring
a שלמים? shlamim? דאיתמר, de'itmar, it was taught, בני רבי חייא ורבי
יהושע בן לוי. bnei Rabi Chiya v'Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi. חד אמר
יתרו קודם מתן תורה היה וחד אמר יתרו אחר מתן תורה היה.
chad amar Yisro kodem matan Torah haya vechad amar Yisro achar matan
Torah haya. It was a debate. So the גמרא Gemara says, fine,
למאן דאמר יתרו קודם מתן תורה היה, leman de'amar Yisro kodem matan
Torah haya, if you insist that יתרו Yitro was before מתן תורה,
matan Torah, קסבר שלמים הקריבו בני נח. kasavar shlamim hikrivu bnei Noach.
You're right, you have to conclude that בני נח bnei Noach brought
a שלמים shlamim because יתרו Yitro brought a שלמים. shlamim. So if
it was before מתן תורה, matan Torah, that's what you wind up
holding, that בני נח bnei Noach can bring a שלמים. shlamim. But
if you hold that בני נח bnei Noach can't bring a שלמים,
shlamim, you'll assert that יתרו Yitro came after מתן תורה matan Torah
and that יתרו Yitro converted. So some disagree with this ברייתא braita
then. Yeah, exactly, what we said, it was a debate whether only
בני נח bnei Noach can bring, whether בני נח bnei Noach can
only bring an עולה olah or can they even bring a שלמים.
shlamim. Okay, so now I have to tell my favorite joke about
יתרו קודם מתן תורה, Yisro kodem matan Torah, which is, so this
kid, this father's learning with his son about פרשת יתרו Parshas Yisro
and says, you know, וישמע יתרו כהן מדין חתן משה. Vayishma Yisro
kohein Midyan chosein Moshe. So he's translating it into Yiddish. So he
says, you know, יתרו, Yisro, the גלח galach פון fun מדין, Midyan,
משהס Moshe's שווער, shver, right, the priest from Midyan, but גלח galach
is a word that sort of means like a Catholic priest, from
מדין, Midyan, משהס Moshe's שווער, shver, Moshe's father-in-law. So the kid says,
but טאטי, Tati, he says, a גלח galach doesn't have קינדער, kinder,
a priest doesn't have kids. So the father thinks and he thinks
and says, this was before מתן תורה. matan Torah. All right, anyway,
so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara said, all right, so anyway, so
that's the issue. יתרו Yitro was before מתן תורה. matan Torah. Anyway,
so that's the debate. Now I do have to say, you know,
Michael made this point, which I just thought about, Michael made this
point about what is this idea that בני נח bnei Noach couldn't
bring a שלמים. shlamim. So any explanation of this, you know, usually
leads to some type of a, you know, statement about the inherent
superiority of בני ישראל, bnei Yisrael, which obviously, you know, of Jews,
which obviously, you know, is something that I find very disturbing. I
mean, Michael said it in a nicer way. You don't have to
say it's somehow we're innately somehow superior, but after הר סיני, Har
Sinai, you know, that greater closeness to God that comes through שמירת
המצוות shemiras hamitzvos allows for that greater intimacy. It's true, the idea
of, I mean, well, what is true is that the idea of
a שלמים shlamim is a greater sense of intimacy, you know, it's
not you give it to God and you go home. It's like
the phrase of the גמרא Gemara is like משולחן גבוה קזכו. mishulchan
gavoah kazehu. You're there eating from the same meat and from the
same animal, it's almost like you're sharing a meal with God. I
mean, it's almost, you know, you could see how it could also
feel to a certain degree like almost like a little pagan, right,
you're sharing this meal with God. But so, and you know, and
so it's a little bit interesting. Like בני נח bnei Noach can
bring sacrifices everywhere. They, you know, to God, right, they're allowed to
have במות, bamot, okay, which seems like that's a little bit more
threatening in terms of leading to idolatry and paganism and an idea
of multiple gods as opposed to a central single location or whatever.
On the other hand, you know, they're not, they have to bring
an עולה, olah, you know, we, you know, could bring a שלמים.
shlamim. I know, maybe that's the balance or somehow. If we're bringing
one central location, it's less of a concern that it leads to
these more sort of pagan attitudes, so maybe it allows for something
like a שלמים shlamim which could be seen as a little riskier.
But it is true, now again in my looking at Milgrom I
tried to see, you know, I don't think that there's any evidence
that this is historically true, you know, although I tried to explore
this last night, I have to explore it some more. Is there
any historical evidence that, you know, sacrifices in the ancient world were
all just about you offer and you leave? How much was there,
was there a concept of sacrifices as you actually share from some
of the meat? Because you have to admit that it's pretty radical,
right? Besides this idea it's like you're eating a meal with God,
it's also like if the thing is sanctified, right, and it's holy
and it means like you can't, you know, the whole concept of
sanctified which sort of suggests that you can't touch it, it's totally
off-limits, it all goes to God and so on. So there is
a very radical concept here with this idea, you know, with this
idea of a שלמים, shlamim, and the גמרא Gemara is saying that
that was like limited to בני ישראל. bnei Yisrael. So at least
according to this opinion. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: כתנאי. Kitannai. This question about when יתרו Yitro came is a
debate of תנאים, Tannaim, before, after מתן תורה. Matan Torah. Again, we're
assuming according to this approach that explains he brought a שלמים Shelamim
after מתן תורה, Matan Torah, that he also converted, which is a
separate point. Okay, but this question is a debate of תנאים, Tannaim,
because it says: וישמע יתרו כהן מדין. Vayishma Yitro Kohen Midyan. So
יתרו Yitro heard and he came. מה שמועה שמע ובא? Ma shmua
shama uva? What made him hear? What made him come? ונתגייר. Venityayer.
And here's the keyword ונתגייר, Venityayer, right, which is funny because later
we know that it sounds like יתרו Yitro maybe did not follow
them in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, maybe he went back home, right?
וילך לו אל ארצו, Vayelech lo el artzo, so on, but anyway,
according to this he converted. At what stage did he come? Okay,
ונתגייר. Venityayer. At what stage? So let's take a look. רבי יהושע
אומר: Rabbi Yehoshua omer: מלחמת עמלק שמע ובא. milchemet Amalek shama uva.
Like the what occurs right before פרשת יתרו, Parshat Yitro, the war
with עמלק, Amalek, שכתב בצדו ויחלש יהושע את עמלק ואת עמו לפי
חרב. sheketiv betzido vayachalosh Yehoshua et Amalek ve'et amo lefi charev. And
then the next verse right after עמלק Amalek is יתרו Yitro heard
and came. And that would put him before מתן תורה. Matan Torah.
רבי אלעזר המודעי אומר: Rabbi Elazar Hamodai omer: מתן תורה שמע ובא.
Matan Torah shama uva. He heard the מתן תורה, Matan Torah, so
he came after the events of מתן תורה, Matan Torah, after the
events that occur later in פרשת יתרו. Parshat Yitro. Okay, which by
the way, is the reason that that works or whatever, even though
it's so much against the chronology of the פסוקים, pesukim, is because
יתרו Yitro sees משה Moshe spending all of his day judging the
people, makes a lot more sense if that was after מתן תורה.
Matan Torah. Okay, כשניתנה תורה לישראל, keshenitna Torah leYisrael, because when the
תורה Torah was given to the Jewish people, היה קולו הולך מסוף
העולם ועד סופו. haya kolo holech misof ha'olam ve'ad sofo. God's voice,
thundering voice, was heard from one end of the world to the
other. וכל מלכי עובדי כוכבים אחזתן רעדה בהיכליהן. vechol malchei ovdei kochavim
achazatan ra'ada beheichalehen. All the idolatrous kings, they were filled with trembling
in their castles. ואמרו שירה, ve'amru shira, and they sang out in
praise to God, שנאמר ובהיכלו כולו אומר כבוד. shene'emar uveheichalo kulo omer
kavod. In His castle, everybody says glory and honor. נתקבצו כולם אצל
בלעם הרשע. Nitkabtzu kulam etzel Bilam harasha. They went to בלעם, Bilam,
right? He was their one prophet who gave them some access into
what was going on. ואמרו לו, ve'amru lo, and they said to
him, מה קול ההמון הזה אשר שמענו? ma kol hahamon hazeh asher
shamanu? What is this thunderous voice that we heard? שמא מבול בא
לעולם? shema mabul ba la'olam? Maybe God is going to flood the
world? So he said to them, השם למבול ישב, Hashem lemabul yashav,
אמר להם, amar lahem, God sat over the מבול, mabul, וישב השם
מלך לעולם. vayeshev Hashem melech le'olam. כבר נשבע הקדוש ברוך הוא שאינו
מביא מבול לעולם. kevar nishba Hakadosh Baruch Hu she'eino meivi mabul la'olam.
God has already sworn that He won't bring a מבול mabul to
the world. אמרו לו, amru lo, מבול של מים אינו מביא, mabul
shel mayim eino meivi, fine, he said he won't bring a flood
of water, אבל מבול של אש מביא, aval mabul shel esh meivi,
maybe, maybe He'll bring a flood of fire? שנאמר כי הנה השם
באש נשפט. shene'emar hinei Hashem ba'esh nishpat. We knew a lot of
פסוקים, pesukim, even פסוקים pesukim way before they were given. God is
going to judge with fire. אמר להם, amar lahem, כבר נשבע שאינו
משחית כל בשר. kevar nishba she'eino mashchit kol basar. No, he said
that he said I won't destroy all flesh. He's not going to
destroy it anyway, whether with water or whether with fire. So then
they said to him, ומה קול ההמון הזה ששמענו? uma kol hahamon
hazeh sheshamanu? What is this thunderous voice that we heard? It's pretty
interesting, they heard a thunderous voice, they sang שירה shira without knowing
what it was about. But I guess, you know, you hear thunderous
voices and you're afraid that, you know, God is angry or whatever
you're afraid, you know, you respond with some religious response before you
figure out what it's about. You gotta cover your bases. Anyway, so
they said, so what is this? אמר להם, amar lahem, חמדה טובה
יש לו בבית גנזיו. chemda tova yesh lo beveit genazav. God has
a very desirous treasure in His treasure houses, שגנוזה אצלו תתקע"ד דורות,
shegenuza etzlo tish'ah me'ot veshiv'im ve'arba'ah dorot, that has been hidden by
Him, it's been stored up with Him 974 generations before the world
was created, קודם שנברא העולם. kodem shenivra ha'olam. Okay, which is very
interesting that you can have an idea of generations before the world
was created, but anyway, but this is the idea of how long
God has been waiting to give the תורה, Torah, not just from
the time of the creation of the world, from 974 generations, not
years, generations before the world was created, God already had the תורה,
Torah, all of this wait just to be able to give the
תורה Torah to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Okay, וביקש ליתנה לבניו, ubikesh
litna levanav, he wanted to give it to his children, שנאמר השם
עוז לעמו יתן. shene'emar Hashem oz le'amo yiten. Now partly also רש"י
Rashi says this is also the פסוק pasuk about דבר צוה לאלף
דור. davar tziva le'elef dor. The דבר, davar, God's word, was commanded
after אלף דור, elef dor, after a thousand generations. Okay, and that's
what this tremendous thundering is, finally after a thousand generations God is
now able to do and give this תורה Torah to בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael. מיד פתחו כולם ואמרו, miyad patchu kulam ve'amru, they all
opened up and said, השם יברך את עמו בשלום. Hashem yivarech et
amo vashalom. Oh, they recognized the uniqueness, the chosenness of Israel, God
should bless His people with peace. רבי אלעזר אומר... Rabbi Elazar omer...
so anyway, that's the version that he came after מתן תורה. Matan
Torah. Now, רבי אלעזר אומר: Rabbi Elazar omer: קריעת ים סוף שמע
ובא. kri'at Yam Suf shama uva. He came after the splitting of
the ים סוף, Yam Suf, which puts it chronologically where the פסוקים
pesukim are, but that that was somehow more motivated him than מלחמת
עמלק. milchemet Amalek. שנאמר ויהי כשמוע כל מלכי האמורי, vayehi kishmo'a kol
malchei ha'Emori, when all of them heard, you know, and the... it
says in יהושע Yehoshua and they were not able to stand up
because they were filled with trembling when they heard about the splitting
of the ים סוף. Yam Suf. So it was that that was
so awesome that made him come. Now, I should just say it's
interesting to think about these three different approaches, right, if you want
to think about like what motivates somebody to convert. convert or to
come to בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, right? So the idea of like
the splitting of the ים סוף Yam Suf that maybe is like
the most obvious in the sense of like it is the supernatural
wonder.
It's something that speaks about God protecting His people, destroying their enemies.
You don't want to be on the enemy's side, you
want to be on God's people's side, right? So that's like the
splitting of the ים סוף. Yam Suf. עמלק Amalek is similar, except
the difference with עמלק Amalek is that it's more God operating within
nature, rather than supernatural, right? And so like maybe, you know, so
that's an interesting question, sort of like that Mark Twain thing about
the Jewish people and the famous Mark Twain essay about like how
they've survived and the Romans haven't. Do you sort of see somehow
somebody who's like maybe not impressed by pyrotechnics or by supernatural wonders,
it's more sort of like seeing God operating in an everyday, so
it shows that God, in something more natural, shows maybe a more
of a sustained sense of God being with these people. And then
of course the idea of the תורה Torah is very different. The
idea of the תורה Torah is not God's protection, the idea of
the תורה Torah is actually about the מצוות mitzvot and the relationship
with God, that that sort of represents. So it's interesting in thinking
about these different models of what would make somebody come to convert.
Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says, now that we're talking about
this verse about how all the kings heard about the splitting of
the ים סוף Yam Suf and they trembled, they say ואף רחב
הזונה אמרה לשלוחי יהושע, ve'af Rachav ha'Zonah amrah lishluchei Yehoshua, רחב Rachav
the prostitute said to יהושע's Yehoshua spies, very like echoing this verse
about when it's described how the kings of כנען Canaan heard about
the splitting of the sea. She says כי שמענו את אשר הוביש
השם את מי ים סוף, ki shamanu et asher hovish Hashem et
mei Yam Suf, we heard how God caused the waters of the
ים סוף Yam Suf to dry up. Actually, I think the earlier
verse about the kings of כנען Canaan was about the splitting of
the ירדן, Yarden, and that רחב Rachav was talking about the splitting
of the ים סוף. Yam Suf. Anyway, מאי שנא התם דאמר ולא
היה בם עוד רוח? mai shna hatam de'amar velo hayah bam od
ruach? By the earlier verse it says that the kings did not
have any spirit, they didn't have once they heard about the wonders
that God had done, ומאי שנא הכא גבי רחב umai shna hacha
gabei Rachav when she's repeating it says ולא קמה עוד רוח באיש,
velo kamah od ruach be'ish, spirit didn't stand up in a person.
So what's the emphasis of the word stand up when it uses
it in the context of רחב Rachav describing more or less the
same phenomenon? So the גמרא Gemara says, top of קיז עמוד ב,
Kuf Tet Zayin amud bet, דאפילו אקשויי נמי לא אקשו. de'afillu akshuyei
nami lo akshu. So this is obviously focusing on the fact that
רחב Rachav was a prostitute, so the word קמה kamah which is
like to stand up or erect, that they were not even able
to have an erection. People were so devastated and fearful that they
couldn't even sexually have an erection because she was a prostitute. ומנא
ידעה umena yad'ah and how did she know that nobody was able
to do it, so no man? דאמר מר אין לך כל שר
ונגיד שלא בא על רחב הזונה de'amar mar ein lecha kol sar
venagid shelo ba al Rachav ha'Zonah because she had her, she had
the clientele of all of the kings and all of the officers,
so she was able to accurately report this. Okay, אמרו בת י'
שנים היתה, amru bat yud shanim haytah, she was ten years old
כשצאו ישראל ממצרים keshe'yatzu Yisrael mi'Mitzrayim when they left Egypt, וזנתה כל
מ' שנה vezantah kol mem shanah and for 40 years she was
involved in prostitution, שהיו ישראל במדבר shehayu Yisrael bamidbar the whole 40
years they were in the wilderness. אחר חמשים שנה achar chamishim shanah
and then she was 50 years old, נתגיירה nitgayrah she converted once
they were coming into the land and destroying יריחו Yericho and conquering
יריחו. Yericho. אמרה amrah and she said, יהא מחול לי בשכר חבל
חלון ופשתים. yehei machul li bischar chevel chalon ufishtim. So that that
I am going to lower down this rope by the window, and
she hid them in the flax, that will atone for me for
all of my 40 years of sinning and the way רש"י Rashi
explains it is that those were also things that she used in
her prostitution, that people would maybe sneak into the window or she
would hang out a string as a sign, she would hide the
people that were using her services in the flax. So these were
things that were also tools of her prostitution and now she's using
them in order to support בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. Okay, אמר מר.
amar mar. So that's the end of the idea of that whether
בני נח Bnei Noach can only bring an עולה olah or can
they even bring a שלמים. shlamim. ועובדי כוכבים בזמן הזה רשאים לעשות
כן. ve'ovdei kochavim bazman hazeh resha'im la'asot ken. But now we switch
to the idea that although interestingly non-Jews are not allowed to bring
according to the הלכה, halachah, again this isn't exactly describing what happens
historically, but anyway, on the one hand they're limited to עולות, olot,
but on the other hand they are allowed to bring all, they
don't have a single location, they can offer sacrifices to God anywhere.
There's no איסור במות issur bamot that apply to בני נח. Bnei
Noach. Okay, אמר מר ועובדי כוכבים בזמן הזה רשאים לעשות כן. amar
mar ve'ovdei kochavim bazman hazeh resha'im la'asot ken. They can bring sacrifices
wherever they want to God. מנלן? menalan? Where do we know this
from? דתנו רבנן detanu rabanan our rabbis taught, דבר אל בני ישראל.
daber el Bnei Yisrael. This is at the opening of the איסור
issur of slaughtering sacrifices outside of the temple. It says Speak to
בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So בני ישראל מצווין על שחוטי חוץ, Bnei
Yisrael mtzuvin al shechutei chutz, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael are commanded not
to slaughter outside the temple, ואין עובדי כוכבים מצווין על שחוטי חוץ
ve'ein ovdei kochavim mtzuvin al shechutei chutz but non-Jews are not commanded.
ולפיכך כל אחד ואחד בונה לו במה לעצמו. ulifichach kol echad ve'echad
boneh lo bamah le'atzmo. So this is exactly what the גמרא Gemara
sort of says is like the classic example of everybody deciding for
themselves what their religion is, everybody's going to go and build for
him, build for himself. themselves their own במה. bamah. So it's normally
used in like the derogatory, like everybody is going to decide how
they want to keep כשרות kashrus and how they want to keep
שבת, shabbos, everybody goes build their own במה. bamah. But here it's
actually saying no, this actually is what's allowed for בני נח, B'nei
Noach, everybody can have their own private במה. bamah. There's not a
defined central location or central sort of rules of worship or so
on. כל אחד ואחד בונה לו במה לעצמו ומקריב עליה, kol echad
ve'echad boneh lo bamah le'atzmo u'makriv aleha, and can bring sacrifices. כל
מה שירצה, kol mah she'yirtzeh, whatever they want. Okay. Again, with the
כל מה שירצה kol mah she'yirtzeh presumably meaning like the earlier point,
any animal as long as it's kosher, blemished, not blemished, male, female,
okay, but maybe not anything you want because maybe that's that earlier
discussion about עולה Olah versus שלמים. Shelamim. But anyway, they're able to
bring sacrifices anywhere. Okay. Okay. אמר רבי יעקב בר אחא אמר רב
אסי אסור לסייע ולעשות שליחותן. amar Rabi Yaakov bar Aha amar Rav
Assi asur l'sayei'a vela'asot shlichutan. So this becomes very interesting. You, however,
cannot help them. You know, if they say to you, "Hey, I
have a sacrifice I want to bring," you know, you Jew, go
ahead and could you put it on the altar for me? So
that becomes like an interesting question. Is this... if you're putting it
on the altar to God, but it's the non-Jew's sacrifice, you're his
servant, you're working for him, okay, are you transgressing the prohibition of
offering up, you know, sacrifices outside the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Or
is it like, no, it's not my sacrifice, it's his, and he's
allowed to offer sacrifices outside of the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? You
know, so that gets to an interesting question of who defines like
what does it... like is it the act of putting it on
the altar? If you have two different systems of rules, one that
apply for non-Jews and one that apply for Jews, you know, which...
you know, when you're the one doing it but it's his sacrifice,
whose sort of system is this working for? So anyway, it doesn't
sound like here necessarily if you did this you would actually get
כרת, kareis, you might be... you don't get כרת, kareis, but because
this act is forbidden for... because, you know, it's in the end
it's not your sacrifice, it's his, but nevertheless you can't actively be
a part of this, you know? And this gets to this question,
right, like you know there's two things. There's a principle of not
helping somebody do something that's wrong because of מסייע לידי עוברי עבירה,
misayei'a lidey ovrei aveira, you're helping somebody do a sin. But what
if this thing is actually not a sin for that person, but
it's like wrong for you? Okay? And therefore it's not so much
you're helping him sin, but you're connecting to something that is a
problematic phenomenon if it were you who were doing it. Okay, so
that's like the... so it's not clear where the גמרא Gemara. is
coming out here. Is it ממש mamash if it's you bringing even
though it's his sacrifice, if you're putting it on the altar, you're
doing the עבירה? aveira? Or maybe you're not doing the עבירה aveira
but still it's inappropriate for you to be doing this. So תוספות
Tosafos discusses that a little as well. Okay. But so therefore you
cannot directly help him in this, actively, physically help him, ולעשות שליחותן
vela'asot shlichutan and do it like on his behalf. But אמר רבא
וארונהו להו שרי. amar Rava ve'arunehu lehu sharei. That's true, but you
can give him advice and you can give them instruction. So you
can tell the non-Jew who wants to bring on a private במה,
bamah, you can sort of say, you know, "Here, let me go
ahead and tell you like, you know, here's the way to do
it and here's the nice way to bring the sacrifice." Maybe don't
physically because when you physically help them do it, right, even again,
even if it's not a sin for you, you're connected to a
phenomenon that's off-limits for you, right? But to give them advice or
something, that's like a different story. It's an interesting question that comes
up in the context of for example, you know, according to a
whole one whole approach in הלכה halacha which has been... you know,
has become has become very widespread is that to think about like
עבודה זרה avoda zara and you know and other faiths or whatever,
like you know there was a whole period in where Christianity was
considered to be עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and then the הלכה halacha
sort of nuanced that a bit and said, you know, some people
want to argue that now it's not עבודה זרה avoda zara at
all, but anyway but the more dominant position was to nuance and
say it's עבודה זרה avoda zara for Jews, not for non-Jews. Okay.
So, can I go ahead and help a Christian build a church,
right? For something a phenomenon that for me is עבודה זרה avoda
zara but for them is totally permissible? So that would seem like,
uh, that's a bit... that seems very wrong and problematic for you
as a Jew, right, to be doing that since for you this
is you know... but let's say the church burned down and you
want to go ahead and like and help and... and you know
or they... I mean there were cases like this, you know, through
some anti, you know, these... you know, these various hate crimes or
whatever, you know, they've burned them down or whatever and you want
to go ahead and you, you know, they're your neighbors and you
feel bad for them and they helped you when something happened something
similar happened to your synagogue. Can you go ahead and like donate
money to them? Right? So, you know, it's you're helping them, you're
not directly involved, but you know you're helping them build their church,
right? So anyway, so you have something sort of similar in this
גמרא. Gemara Don't actively bring these sacrifices, okay, but you can actually
advise them, you can you know... and כי הא, ki ha, now
we're going to have a case, כי הא דאיפרא הורמיז, ki ha
de-Iphra Hurmiz, let me just read the story, איפרא הורמיז Iphra Hurmiz
אימיה דשבור מלכא. imei de-Shapur Malka. Ifra Hormiz was the mother of
שבור מלכא, Shvor Malka, who was the Persian king. שדר קרבנא לרבא,
shadar korbana le'Rava, she sent a sacrifice to רבא. Rava. שלח ליה,
shlach lei, and she sent to him, אסקיה ניהלי לשם שמים, askeini
ha lei l'Shem Shamayim, offer this up to me to your God
for the sake of heaven, like offer this for me to your
God. But presumably she didn't say this was רבא, Rava, this was
when there was no בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So what was he
going to do? So אמר להו לרב ספרא ולרב אחא בר הונא,
amar lehu le'Rav Safra u'le'Rav Acha bar Huna, so he said to
his two students, רב ספרא Rav Safra and רב אחא בר הונא,
Rav Acha bar Huna, זילו ודברו תרי אומי גולאי, zilu ve'dabru trei
umei gulay, go take two young non-Jews. Okay, don't do it yourselves.
Go take two young non-Jews. וחזו היכא דמסיק ימא סירטא, ve'khazu heikh
de'masika yama sirtu, and go see where the sea has raised up
some silt, meaning a place of land that's been exposed by the
sea, because he wanted everything, he said what's appropriate to do if
you're going to build this, offer this thing, is to do it
on stuff that has not been used for mundane purposes. So get
a plot of land that has just been exposed by the sea,
it hasn't been used for mundane purposes. The מהרש"א Maharsha says maybe
that's also why they wanted these young men because maybe ones that
have not yet like been involved in some, like young that they're
a similar sense of like unused. I mean as a funny idea
to say by people, but you know somebody who has not like
identified with some different trade, so it seems as like, so get
these young men, a place that's just been exposed by the sea,
ושקלו צבי חדתא, ve'shaklu tzivei chadata, go get some unused wood, fresh
wood, ואפיקו נורא ממאנא חדתא, ve'afiku nura mi'mana chadata, and go make
a fire from like a, you know, from like a new stove,
you know, a new fire. Everything should be brand new. ואסקוה ניהלה
לשם שמים, ve'askuni ha lei l'Shem Shamayim, and have these men offer
it on her behalf for heaven. So they're arranging the whole thing,
they're advising it, but they're not physically actively doing it. Okay, and
that's okay. So even though this was forbidden for us to do,
it's not forbidden for them to do, okay, and therefore you can
go ahead and help them in this indirect way. Just don't be
physically actively involved. Yes, what did you want to say? Yes, this
whole idea of idolaters being allowed to have במות. bamot. So she's
in there like taking an assumption, I mean, that they only use
it to make sacrifices to השם? Hashem? Yes, all of this is
if they're offering to God. But is that realistic? No, it's not
realistic, but with a במה bamah in their idolatry. I understand, I
mean, well partly the phrase here of עובדי כוכבים Ovdei Kochavim is
a later gloss. A lot of these early texts, and I didn't
check all don't, you know, עובדי כוכבים Ovdei Kochavim is the later
Jewish censorship of a lot of these texts. Originally the text said
גויים Goyim or נכרים, Nochrim, just like non-Jews, used a generic term.
You're right. Once you use the term here for non-Jews of idolaters,
that's the term you're using. It's ironic because you're saying idolaters can
have these private altars if they use them for God. But the
original text didn't say idolaters, the original text said non-Jews can have
all these altars. But you're right, it still probably even if that
wasn't the word you had in the text, the historical reality was
such that they were pagans and so on. So that is correct.
Yes, all of this assumes a little bit of a non-realistic context.
I mean maybe it happened every now and then like the story,
but you know this is basically a rule for a context in
which nobody is abiding by. Because all the idolaters, first of all
they're not asking Jews what's the הלכה, Halacha, am I allowed to?
You know, they're doing their own thing and they're bringing it to
all their multiple gods. Right. But within the הלכה Halacha system they
are allowed to bring it to God on their private altars and
we're allowed to sort of advise them or indirectly help them, but
we can't directly be involved. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר ליה אביי כמאן, amar lei Abaye ke'man, now who
is this going like that you wanted everything to be fresh and
new? כרבי אלעזר בן שמוע, ke'Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua, like רבי אלעזר
בן שמוע. Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua. דתניא, de'tanya, as we learned in
a braitah, רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua says מה
מזבח שלא נשתמש בו הדיוט, ma mizbe'ach shelo nishtamesh bo hedyot, just
as an altar was something that was never used by a commoner,
אף עצים שלא נשתמש בהן הדיוט, af eitzim shelo nishtamesh bahen hedyot,
so even the wood on the altar has to be fresh and
never used by a commoner. Don't repurpose an old table and throw
it on the altar. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבי אלעזר
בן שמוע בבמה, ve'amar Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua be'bamah, but I don't
understand, this was a במה, bamah, and a במה bamah doesn't he
admit that you're allowed to use old wood on a במה? bamah?
Why was רבא Rava so careful here? Where do we see he
holds that? דתניא, de'tanya, as we learned in a braitah. כתוב אחד
אומר, kasuv echad omer, one verse says ויתן דויד לארנן במקום, Vayiten
David l'Arnan bamokom, דויד David gave to ארנן Arnan for the place
that they were going to use for building the Temple, שקלי זהב
משקל שש מאות, shiklei zahav mishkal shesh meiot, 600 talents or you
know shekel of gold. וכתיב, ukhsiv, and a verse says ויקן דויד
את הגורן ואת הבקר בכסף שקלים חמשים, Vayiken David et hagoren ve'et
habakar bekesef shekalim chamishim, 50, okay, so now we have a problem.
Is it 50 or is it 600? כיצד, keytzad, how do you
reconcile this? גבה מכל שבט ושבט חמשים, gava mikol shevet vashevet chamishim,
so every tribe contributed 50, שהן שש מאות, shehen shesh meiot, which
led to 600. 600. That's a nice resolution. רבי אומר משום אבא
יוסי בן דוסתאי, Rebbi omer mishum Abba Yossi ben Dostai, no, בקר
ועצים ומקום מזבח בשש מאות. bakar v'etzim u'makom mizbeach beshesh meot. No,
what the verse that said 50 was saying was that's what he
paid for the threshing floor and for the cattle. He paid 50.
But for the entire place he paid 600. וכל הבית כולו בשש
מאות. v'chol habayit kulo beshesh meot. That's also another nice resolution. ואלעזר
בן שמואל אומר, v'Elazar ben Shmuel omer, now the same, sounds like
this line is going to sound almost identical, or is identical: בקר
ועצים ומקום מזבח חמשים וכל הבית כולו בשש מאות. bakar v'etzim u'makom
mizbeach chamishim v'chol habayit kulo beshesh meot. דכתיב, dechtiv, ויאמר ארונה אל
דוד יקח ויעל אדני המלך, vayomer Araunah el David yikach v'ya'al Adonai
hamelech, take it and offer it up as a sacrifice, הטוב בעיניו,
hatov b'einav, what is good in your eyes. ראה הבקר לעלה והמרגים
וכלי הבקר לעצים. re'eh habakar l'olah v'hamorgim u'klei habakar l'etzim. Okay, and
this is the point where we're going to get to, not the
600 versus 50, but it says behold, here you can go ahead
and use the, you know, the various farm implements, you can use
them for wood for your sacrifice. Oh, so look, you're using this
old wood, this used wood for sacrifice. It must be that on
a במה bamah you're allowed to repurpose wood. It's only on the
central altar that you're not. So why were they so מקפיד makpid
with this sacrifice they brought for this mother of שבור מלכא? Shvor
Malka? So the גמרא Gemara says, ורבא אמר לך, v'Rava amar lach,
Rava will say to you, התם בחדתי. hatam b'chadati. No, just because
you had these farm implements doesn't mean that they were used. It
could be brand new farm implements, which is still funny because you
would think that if the idea was you wanted fresh wood, right,
it didn't just mean that it hadn't been used, it meant like
it was natural, it was virgin almost. You know, the fact that
it had been cut and fashioned and turned into a farm instrument,
that that, oh well technically you haven't yet used it, it's still
brand new. But okay, that's the answer. So Rava understands that even
for a במה bamah you want everything to be fresh and that's
why he gave this advice to the mother of the שבור מלכא
Shvor Malka for her sacrifice. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: מאי מורגים? mai morgim? What is this מורגים? morgim? אמר עולא
מטה של טורבל. amar Ulla mita shel Turbal. It's a bed of
Turbal. מאי מטה של טורבל? mai mita shel Turbal? What is that?
So אמר אביי עיזא דקרקסא דדיישין ביה. amar Abaye iza d'karkasa d'daishan
beishai. It's like this, you know, it's like this basically, it's like
a plank with these like cleats, like you know, these, these, what
are they, you know, these what they called, pointy things, whatever, spikes.
A plank with like spikes that, you know, like, like that goats
go on it or whatever, you know, basically cows walk on it,
it's like a flat plank that has these spikes underneath it and
you put it on top of the wheat and you have the
cows walk on it and it basically like crushes the wheat. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר אביי מאי קרא,
amar Abaye mai kra, הנה שמתיך למורג חרוץ חדש בעל פיפיות, hinei
samtiha l'morag charutz chadash ba'al pipiyot, behold I have made you למורג,
l'morag, so that's the word מורג, morag, חרוץ חדש charutz chadash of
new, of new like, you know, points, of new, you know, of
new, right, my mind is going, okay anyway, בעל פיפיות, ba'al pipiyot,
right, so of new like, you know, of, you know, of new
spikes, again I can't keep thinking of the word spikes. Of new
spikes, of, you know, of things like with like teeth. So therefore
you see this מורג morag is something that has spikes and teeth
and that's what it is. Okay, now let's just end this up.
מקלע רבא לבריה ורמי ליה, maklei Rava l'brei v'rami lei, so Rava
challenged his son to see if he could resolve this contradiction of
the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, ורמי קראי אהדדי. v'mamlei krayei ahadadi. כתיב, kativ,
one verse says ויתן דוד לארנן v'yiten David l'Ornan etc. and it
says that he gave it to him and it says that it
was 600. וכתיב, u'chtiv, another verse says ויקן דוד vayikan David and
he bought it for 50. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? How do you
resolve it? So גובה מכל שבט ושבט חמשים שהן שש מאות. goveh
mikol shevet v'shevet chamishim she-hein shesh meot. So presumably his son came
up with this answer: oh wait, 50 is one-twelfth of 600, there
were 12 tribes,
so every tribe gave 50, that led to 600. So now the
גמרא Gemara, just has one last remaining question. ואכתי, v'akadi, says the
גמרא, קשיין אהדדי, kashyan ahadadi, התם כסף הכא זהב. hatam kesef hacha
zahav. Wait, we got a problem, because the one that says 50
says that it was 50 of silver and the one that says
600 says 600 of gold. There's a huge difference between gold and
silver. You don't just resolve it by saying each tribe gave 50,
50 times 12 is 600. אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar, גובה
כסף במשקל שש מאות זהב. goveh kesef bemishkal shesh meot zahav. Fine.
So everybody gave silver, but they didn't give 50 silver שקל. shekel.
They gave silver equivalent to 50 שקל shekel of gold. Okay, so
what they actually gave was silver, but its value was 50 שקל
shekel of gold, so times 12 got you your 600 שקל shekel
of gold. Okay, we will end here for today.